Give him praise. Come on, put your hands
together.
Happy New Year.
Wow.
It's great to be in 2019.
The Lord has been gracious to us.
God is a good God.
The testimonies that we have had tonight
have been amazing
stories of God's faithfulness.
And I'm sure that there are many people
who are seated here
with perhaps even better ones.
And that tells us that God is a faithful
God.
Pastor Barasa reminded us that as long
as the presence of God is with us,
you're okay.
Hallelujah.
You're okay.
That is the message of Christmas.
In fact, it's the message I preached on
Christmas Day. Emmanuel,
God with us.
When the presence of God is with us,
you're okay.
You don't have to worry.
And so, even if 2018
proved not to be what you expected it to
be,
God is still alive.
Hallelujah.
Sometimes you read the stories of God's
people
and how God relates with them,
and reminds me of uh
Fiddler on the Roof. Anybody watched
Fiddler on the Roof?
Tevye says, after he sees his cow is
is hurt, limping, cannot
move around.
He's a poor man.
His daughters are not married.
And yet the butcher is making so much
money.
He looks at heaven and said, "God,
if this is what you do with the chosen
people,
why don't you choose others?"
Anybody else ever felt like that?
Why don't you choose others?
Because the people who are chosen don't
seem to be doing as well
as those who are not
chosen.
But the presence of God makes the
difference.
Hallelujah.
What an exciting time we have had
dancing in the presence of God ever
since we entered in this place,
climaxing on the countdown.
And as the year turned from 2018 to
2019,
I almost lost my voice
and people almost broke my ribs
as they squeezed breath out of my life.
Happy New Year.
Hallelujah.
If you did not give somebody a hug, just
stand and hug them and give them a happy
New Year.
If you are not hugged,
stand there and be hugged.
Hallelujah.
Amen.
Nobody wants to hug the other, okay?
Happy
New Year.
That's what I want to talk about.
Happy
New Year.
That's what I want to talk about.
For the next few weeks,
that is how we are going to greet one
another.
Isn't it?
On text messages, on WhatsApp,
on emails,
when we meet,
happy
New Year.
That is going to be our greetings.
But having gone through several of such
transitions from one year
to another,
I have seen a few
such transitions
as you can guess.
They are n plus one,
where n is any number greater than 40.
So, I think I've seen a number of such
transitions from one year
to another.
And every transition,
it gets sweeter and sweeter,
more exciting,
just like we have had tonight.
But I come to realize that
these wishes of happy New Year,
I know that my message may not be very
exciting,
have absolutely no impact
on how the year turns out.
How many of you have experienced this?
By
end of January,
we are tired of saying happy New Year.
In fact, in March, if you tell somebody
happy New Year, they'll be looking at
you like,
"What What do you mean?"
What do you mean? Because it is over,
isn't it? Happy New Year is over.
So, it really has no impact on our lives
unless
we are determined
to have a happy
New Year.
It takes a determination
to actually enjoy a happy New Year.
And having evaluated what it is that
contributes
to enjoying a happy life,
I have come to the conclusion
that
a truly happy life
does not come merely by a crossover from
one year to another.
I see a few people nodding their heads.
But you are here to enjoy happy New
Year.
Isn't it?
To the contrary,
because of the high expectations that we
put on the dawn of a New Year,
the turn
from one year to another has the
potential
of bringing it with it
great disappointment.
Isn't it?
One of the sisters who testified here,
who is also my very good friend all the
way from the days of current,
accused me of not saying the right
things last year
because a happy New Year did not turn
as happy as she had expected.
And that is a testimony that many can
can give.
So, a crossover does not make a happy
New Year.
And because of the very many
expectations, disappointments that come
as a result of those expectations are
many.
What then must we do
if we are to experience a true sense of
joy that lasts through the year?
If you are to enjoy a truly happy New
Year that does not end with January,
okay? That goes takes you through to the
end of the year. That you can come to
December and you can say, "This truly
was a happy year."
Is Is it actually possible?
Is it possible?
I hear a few
Is it possible to have a happy year
that lasts from January
all the way to December?
It is possible.
The Bible is full of
very practical instructions
and very practical advices on how to
enjoy a happy life
in this world,
not just in the world to come.
You read through the book of Psalms,
there's many of them, Proverbs,
Ecclesiastes,
and many others outline things that one
can do to enjoy a truly happy life.
Jesus himself in the Sermon on the Mount
gave a whole list
of what one can do to experience what he
called a blessed life, which other
translations say a happy life.
And he said, "Blessed are
Have you heard of that in the Sermon on
the Mount? Blessed are and he gives a
list. Blessed are those who do this and
blessed are those who
That word he uses there as which is
translated as blessed, actually it means
happy.
Happy.
So, if you just take the Beatitudes
and read through them
and do them
you can actually live
a happy life.
Now, the problem is when you read what
Jesus is talking about in the
Beatitudes, they are contrary to
our expectations.
That's why we set them aside and look
for other things
that we can do so that we can be happy.
Isn't it?
Because you read
Blessed are you when people persecute
you.
You say, "No, no, no. Let's leave that
aside.
Let's look for a way of living
a happy life."
We do not have time to explore all of
these things that has written for us in
the scriptures.
But I recently read this text of
scriptures and it had a great impact
on my thinking
and my life
because it encapsulates practical ideas
that we can
actually put into practice
and begin to enjoy a happy life.
I shared this with uh our members of
staff at the head office as we closed
the office.
Just
some practical things and I want to
ask to turn to Philippians chapter 4.
Philippians chapter 4, we'll read from
verse 2 to 9.
Philippians chapter 4 verse 2
to 9. Are you there?
Philippians should not be too difficult
to get.
It is on the screen.
I thank God for the people up there.
They're amazing at how they get these
scriptures.
Can you give them a clap?
Amen.
Philippians chapter 4 verse 2 to 9.
We'll read together. I plead with you,
Euodia, and I plead with Syntyche to
agree with each other in the Lord.
Rejoice in the Lord always. And I say it
again, rejoice.
Let your gentleness be evident to all.
The Lord is near.
Do not be anxious about anything, but in
everything by prayer and petition with
thanksgiving present your requests to
God.
And the peace of God, which transcends
all understanding, will guard your
hearts and your minds in Christ Jesus.
Finally, brothers, whatever is true,
whatever is noble, whatever is right,
whatever is pure, whatever is lovely,
whatever is admirable, if anything is
excellent or praiseworthy, think about
such things.
Whatever you have learned or received or
heard from me or seen in me put into
practice.
And the God of peace will be with you.
Amen.
Hallelujah.
If you want to live a happy life
there is a secret
in those few verses.
And so, out of this I want to speak to
us a message I've
entitled The Secret to a Happy New Year.
The secret
to a happy new year. Of course, this is
not a secret at all. It is already
written
in the Bible, which all of us have.
But Paul gives in this particular
section of scripture seven basic
instructions
to the Philippians
which I believe, if we take seriously in
our lives
I believe you can live a happy new year
from January
to December.
Seven instructions
that he gives to the Philippians
in this verse in this verses.
I have given them titles, so
The first one
is release your enemies.
Release
your enemies.
The second one, reconcile
your friends.
The third one, rejoice
in the Lord.
The fourth one respect everyone.
The fifth one, relax
in God.
Hallelujah.
The sixth one, refocus your thinking.
And the seventh one
redirect your walk.
If you list those things, put it in a
card small piece of card, eh?
Put it in your pocket.
When you face any situation, pull your
card out and check which one should I
apply
in this situation?
Are we together?
Or put it in your phone.
Most phones that we have have a
notebook.
Isn't it?
Put it in one of the pages of your
notebooks.
And when you are faced with a situation,
find out what should I apply in this
situation? I'll explain them very
quickly.
The first one, release your enemies.
We'll see from verse number two.
To enjoy a peaceful life a happy life
you must release your enemies.
Paul writes to the Philippians and tells
them, "I plead with you, Euodia,
and I plead with Syntyche to agree with
each other in the Lord."
Euodia and Syntyche, we are told, were
key pillars in the work.
Each one was prominent in her own right.
Their devotion to the work of God and to
God himself was very deep.
Their commitment to the cause of the
Lord Jesus Christ was unquestionable.
Their support for Paul and his team was
generous.
Paul refers to them as women who have
contended at my side in the cause of the
gospel. These women were strong women
who stood by Paul through thick and
through thin.
They contended for the sake of the
gospel by Paul's side. They were a
pillar in Paul's ministry.
Euodia
and Syntyche.
But for some unexplained reasons
these two women could not see eye to
eye. How do you serve in Paul's ministry
and you can't talk to one another?
How do you serve in the ushering
ministry and you can't talk to one
another? How you do you sing in the same
choir and you cannot talk to one
another, choir members?
How do you serve with the bishop like
Pastor Obara is saying and you cannot
talk
with one another?
These two people really were serious
born again Christians serving in the
ministry
but for whatever reasons, they could not
see eye
to eye.
They fought over everything.
They fought over anything.
Their disagreements were so bad that
word reached Paul in prison
where he was incarcerated in Ro- in
Roman prison.
And so, Paul felt so disturbed that he
wrote a letter to the Philippians and
say,
"I plead with Euodia and Syntyche
to agree with each other."
And he adds there,
"in the Lord."
One of the things that is sure to rob
you of your joy and happiness
during this year
is disagreement.
If you have a person with whom you
cannot see eye to eye,
if you have a person when you are coming
for a happy new year crossover Kesha,
they sat on this side and you sat on
this side because you want to make sure
you do not meet or your eyes do not meet
or if you are told to hug one another,
you do not
accidentally hug.
You
don't like that person. That is a simple
one.
You hate that person.
You do not like them. You do not love
them.
And so, you are in total disagreement.
You hate one another. You can consider
that person your enemy.
Be assured that if you have such a
person in your life,
it is very unlikely that you'll enjoy a
happy new year.
In fact, let me make it worse, which is
true.
The closer that person is to you in
relationship,
the worse it is for you.
A poor relationship with your spouse,
with your husband or your wife,
a bad relationship as a parent
with your child
or as a child with your parents or uh
with your boss at your place of work or
with your colleague at your place of
work or with a close friend who you
consider to be close to you and you
somehow have come to a disagreement over
something that pricks your heart when
you think about it is sure to rob you of
happiness in 2019.
And unless you deal with it,
you are not going to enjoy 2019.
Are we together?
So, you must make a choice this first
day of 2019, this very first few hours
of 2019 to release that person from your
heart.
To just say, "I forgive this person.
I
want to overcome that disagreement. I
give up on that hatred and I want to
enjoy my year."
Amen.
That is a decision that God cannot make
for you.
That is a decision that you must make
yourself.
So, if you are here
and you have a spouse that you do not
talk to,
you disagreed and you cannot see eye to
eye, and you are still also determined
to enjoy a happy new year,
I am telling you,
release that person
in your heart.
Because
otherwise, you are in a futile exercise.
You will come out of this service, you
will meet at the parking lot and your
happy new year
is gone.
It's gone.
Isn't it?
It's finished.
Finished.
So, if you are serious in enjoying a
happy new year, you must get rid of
every form of anger, every form of
bitterness, every form of hatred that
you have harbored against anybody in
your circle of relationships.
Release all of these people
and just cleanse your heart
and say, "Lord, I want to enjoy 20 19."
Forgive them.
Whatever they did,
Paul advises the Romans in Romans
chapter 12,
verse 18.
And he says, "If it is possible, and I
know it is possible,
as far as it depends on you, and it
depends on you,
live at peace with everyone."
Live at peace with everyone.
Do not take revenge, my friends, but
leave room for God's wrath, for it is
written, "It is mine to avenge. I will
repay," says the Lord.
Brothers and sisters, these are not
theories that are put in the scriptures
for reading.
These are practical things that we can
do.
I have those of you who are from Valley
Road, you would remember because I do
remember. I have stood in this pulpit
and given you a testimony
of a person who wronged me. I don't have
too many enemies. In fact, as I stand
here, I don't think I have any enemy
that I can think of.
But this particular person was like as
Alexander the coppersmith in my life,
who did me great harm.
And one time as I was reading the
scriptures, the spirit of God quickened
in my heart that I should forgive this
person and move on.
And I found that it was not possible.
So, I prayed.
And the Bible the the the part that I
was reading was actually the Beatitudes
at that time. And say, "If your enemy is
hungry,
give him to eat."
And I said, "Lord, this is not
practically possible."
And
as I was praying and reading the word of
God, the spirit of God quickened in my
heart that I have to do it. And so, I
knelt down and I prayed and I said,
"God, give me the grace
to forgive,
but also give me the grace to love."
Soon after that prayer,
my phone rang.
God is amazing. He acts quickly
on such matters.
My phone rang
and this person called.
And you know, most people who hurt you
don't even know they have hurt you.
And even if they know, they don't care.
And so, this person called and say, "Ah,
brother David, hey!
You know,
how are you?" And we talk, we talk.
And he says he wanted me to do something
for him, something very significant,
which I only could do for him.
And the Lord tells me, "This is your
opportunity
to express love
to this person."
And I did. And with joy, I went out and
did that which was in my ability to do
for this person.
That was many years ago and that person
is is not in this congregation, so don't
bother guessing
whether it is you or somebody else.
But from that day,
this person became one of my best
friends to this day.
The blessings that this person has
poured into my life amazing.
Release your enemies
if you want to enjoy a happy
new year.
A couple
owed me
a lot of money.
I don't want to give the details
because this is also being broadcast, so
they may be watching.
But it was a lot of money by my
standards.
I'm not talking in thousands, pastor.
It's the kind of money that has never
seen my account.
But it accumulated over a period of time
ranging to over 1 million shillings.
At first, I thought they didn't have
money, but finally I discovered they
just didn't want to pay.
So, I took did after trying all the
best, praying for them, doing
everything,
so that they could give me this money,
and they were not giving.
Finally, I thought the best thing to do
is the Bible says, "If you don't can't
do this and they do they do,
finally you do what is necessary. So, I
got a lawyer
to write a very strong letter
to these people.
So, the lawyer wrote a strong letter
They got a lawyer who wrote a stronger
letter.
And the spirit of God at that time told
me,
"This is not the battle I called you to
fight.
Release these people."
I released them.
And I said,
"I don't need that money
anymore."
Few months later,
the Lord in his own divine wisdom and
provision
gave me
several times
the money they owed me.
Several times. I won't tell you how many
times.
Just in case you follow me.
But it was long time ago, so the MONEY
IS FINISHED.
BROTHERS AND SISTERS, to enjoy a happy
life, don't hold anybody in your life.
Don't hold. Release. Just give them up.
Just say, "Lord, I have forgiven. But
also go and tell them, if it is
possible, I have forgiven you.
I've released you.
You will enjoy a happy life. Because do
you know what?
When you have an oath against a person,
when you have bitterness and rage and
anger and all those things against a
person, they keep appearing in your
sight.
Have you noticed?
You go to town and there they are.
You go to church and there they are. You
go home and there they are.
And
every time you see them, something burns
within your heart and your happy new
year
is over.
If you're going to enjoy a happy new
year,
I plead with you, dear,
and I plead with Syntyche to agree with
each other in the Lord. Hallelujah.
Because it can only happen in the Lord.
Humanly speaking, it cannot happen
because it is not by might, it is not by
power, but it is by the spirit of the
Lord. Hallelujah. Number two.
Number two.
Reconcile
fighting friends.
Paul writes to the Philippians in verse
number three and say,
"Yes, I ask you, loyal yokefellow, help
these women who have contended at my
side in the course of the gospel, along
with Clement and the rest of my fellow
workers, whose names are in the book of
life." Imagine.
These people, their names are already in
the book of life, but here on earth they
are doing what? Fighting.
So, fighting is not just for sinners.
Sometimes you have seen pastors cut one
another with pangas, isn't it? And their
names are in the book of life.
Yokefellows.
So, Paul says, "Church, church,
help these people."
Sometimes people are not able to
reconcile themselves. If you want to
enjoy a happy life, reconcile your
friends and relatives.
There is nothing as distressing as
living in a war zone.
Do you know that?
Even if you are not personally involved
in the battle, watching people fight
around you will rob you of joy and
happiness.
If your parents are always quarreling
with each other or fighting,
if your colleagues are consistently at
war,
if your friends cannot see eye to eye,
there is no way you can enjoy a happy
new year.
Because you are living literally
in war zone.
You cannot enjoy life in a war zone. So,
for your sake,
reconcile these people.
Do something. Tell them, "You, dear,
Syntyche, please come.
Please tell me what is the issue.
You are both born again.
You are going to heaven. In fact, your
names are written
in the book of life. So, what is the
problem?
Sit down with them and try and reconcile
them. Bring them together to agree so
that in their peace
there are also will be your peace.
In your peace,
in their peace also will be your peace.
Jesus said,
"Blessed are the peacemakers,
for they shall be called the children of
God."
Blessed are the peacemakers. Happy
are the peacemakers. In other words, if
you want to be happy,
be a peacemaker.
When you see people fighting, you tell
them,
"Please, don't
fight one another."
Moses was a peacemaker.
He saw
two Jews fighting.
He came to them and said,
"Brethren, what what is the problem?"
Do you know what they told him?
"Who made you judge over us?"
You know?
So, some people will be rude, but just
try.
Try your best to be a peacemaker. Bring
peace among warring factions. Don't take
sides.
This country is known for war.
Isn't it? Especially around
election times.
Many of us are involved in that battle.
And your peace is stolen away from you.
You watch TV, you see a person, "Every
time I see this person, I just lose
peace."
Am I speaking to someone?
Don't put up your hand.
Instead of doing that,
why don't you try and bring peace?
The whole of last year, early last year,
until the famous handshake, I literally
spent my life
trying
to bring peace
among these people.
My wife is here, she can tell you.
Day,
night, day,
night,
trying to bring peace.
So, when the handshake took place,
you can be sure I enjoyed a happy new
year.
Are you together?
Instead of being angry and adding fuel
to the fire, be a peacemaker.
Because when the country at peace since
March last year,
haven't we been at peace?
Who has been enjoying?
Us.
But when you are adding fuel, he he he
he he he, you know? When I see you, I
just feel like
No. Be a peacemaker.
Be a peacemaker.
Number three.
Rejoice in the Lord.
I like this one.
The secret to happiness
is rejoicing.
Paul says in verse four, "Rejoice in the
Lord." How many times?
Always. Is it possible?
Is it possible to rejoice always?
Some people are saying yes, some are
saying no.
Some are saying yes in the head, but
saying no in the heart.
Others saying yes in the heart, and
saying no in the head.
Paul knew that it was difficult, so he
said, "Again, I say it, rejoice."
Because he thought, "These people may
think, you can't rejoice in the Lord
always. You can't rejoice always."
So, he say, "Again, I say, rejoice." The
truth and reality of life is that it's
made up of twists and turns, ups and
downs.
It is guaranteed and Pastor Obara
brought it out clearly.
He said, "I'm going to disappoint you."
And yes, let me add to that
disappointment.
The new year is going to come with its
own troubles.
It's going to come with its own
challenges for every one of us.
When Paul exhorts us to rejoice, it is
not because it will be nice and dandy
throughout the year.
But rather, it is a call to take a
positive attitude, a positive approach
to life knowing that God is in control.
That's why he says, "Rejoice
in the Lord."
The psalmist had such an attitude as he
approached each day. He declared in
Psalm 118:24,
which I want to prescribe as a pill for
every morning.
Take this before breakfast.
Immediately you wake up,
read Psalm 118:
24. What does it say?
"This is the day that the Lord has made.
I will rejoice and be glad in it."
Say that before you step out.
Before you meet with the realities of
life.
Before things begin to turn other way
the other way round.
Many times when we pray with my wife, I
pray this prayer.
"This is the day that the Lord has made.
I will rejoice and be glad in it."
It sets the mood.
In fact, there's a time when my phone
could take uh
uh could take songs
for alarm.
And so, I had a song with this verse as
my alarm
for waking me up.
So that when I wake up,
it tells me, "This is the day
that the Lord has made. I'm going to
rejoice and be glad in it irrespective
of what the day is about to bring."
Let me tell you, when you face life with
that positive attitude, even when
somebody calls you Mjinga wewe, you
already have a buffer.
Are we together?
When you get onto the roads and you see
people overlapping and want to hit you,
you know that the Lord has already given
you a day that you're supposed to
rejoice in.
And so, you can rejoice no matter what
the circumstances are because this is
the day that the Lord has made. And he
has made it for you so that you can
rejoice and be glad in it.
It is
us to rejoice in the Lord always, and
again I say, "Rejoice."
I have actually discovered that it is
possible to face every day with joy.
I have
by God's grace, God has given me
a spirit of rejoicing.
I try not to carry too many burdens.
You know?
Mama.
I try not to carry too many burdens.
I try not to carry people.
People are heavy,
brethren.
Some weigh a lot of kilos.
So, you wake up and you wake up with
them
in your heart,
in your mind,
in your spirit.
Release them.
Carry your own load
that God has given you to carry. And
then, rejoice.
Be places where people are talking
positively and talking good things. And
laugh. Just enjoy laughter. Hallelujah.
Some of us don't even know how to laugh.
So, what are you laughing about?
You know, when they see you enjoying
life, it's so what is there to enjoy?
My friend, life is short.
In fact, there's a place
in the next one which is says in verse
number five, "The Lord is near."
God is about to come. Jesus is about to
come.
The other day I learned that they are
already injecting people with those
things, huh?
That Barry Smith told us here many years
ago would happen.
It is now being done in Europe
and in America.
The Lord is near. So, enjoy this life
while it lasts.
While it lasts.
Why are you carrying a gloomy face
when Jesus'
face was disfigured on your behalf?
Are we together?
The Bible says his face was so
disfigured that you people did not want
to look at him.
Now, you are also walking around with a
face that is disfigured
by sorrows of life
when Jesus himself had been disfigured
on your behalf.
Hallelujah.
"This is the day
that the Lord has made. I will rejoice
and be glad in it wapende
wasipende."
Hallelujah.
"Shetani apende asipende, I am going to
rejoice and be glad in it." Number five.
Number four.
Respect everyone.
Verse five says,
"Let your gentleness be evident to all."
And this is where he said, because
"The Lord is near."
The call here is to conduct ourselves
with a sense of respect for every person
we come across.
We are to be gentle and not rough.
We are not supposed to be fighting with
everyone we meet.
The Bible says in Proverbs chapter 15:1,
"A gentle answer turns away wrath,
but a harsh word stirs up anger."
The truth is, how you respond to
circumstances
will determine whether you enjoy life or
not.
Be gentle with people. Be kind with
people. Do not fight with everyone. Some
of us are so rough.
So rough, by the way,
that you wonder,
"Were they born on the roadside or
what?" You know?
They You are so rough.
And yet, you want to live
a happy
New Year.
You know? There is no way you can enjoy
life
when you are fighting with every person
that comes across to you.
One time I went to an office, an
international office.
Again, I will not give details.
And
from the
guard at the door,
that guard
who was
from a company, security company,
but guarding at this particular office,
international office,
was so kind.
You know?
When I came in, he asked, "So, what do
you want?" He picked my papers, did to
walked with me around,
delivered me to another person who was
equally kind.
That person delivered me to another
person who was equally kind. And I just
thought to myself, "Wow.
This is how offices ought to be."
You know?
All of them so jolly, so happy,
helpful,
really ready to because the guard, when
I told him what I wanted, he said I
didn't have some of the papers that were
necessary. But he said, "Don't worry.
I'll help you. I'll show you what to do.
Come, I take you to the computer. You
can actually download some of these
papers, fill them right here, and you'll
be sorted out." I said, "Wow. What a
nice man."
This is a security guard from a security
company that has been hired. This is not
an official staff of this
particular office. I saw the
every person I went to was just so nice.
I thought to myself, "When I go, I'm
going to write a letter to these people
and just tell them,
you are doing a great job."
So, finally, I was delivered to another
man.
This man
was so bad.
Was so rough.
Called me names. And I'm thinking to
myself, "What have I done?"
Seriously.
What have I done?
Even simple things, simple I asked him,
"So,
what papers should I give to you?"
"Didn't you read in the internet?"
"No, I just asked because I have several
here. Which ones do you want?" "That is
not my job."
I just thought to myself, "What?"
That's when I realized that sometimes we
blame offices when it is individuals.
Because here is one person who stands
out like a sore thumb
in an office where everybody is gentle
and kind.
But this one person stands out with a
foul mood and a foul spirit.
Paul says, "Be gentle." And he says,
"Let your gentleness
be seen by everyone."
When you are gentle and nice to people,
you enjoy life.
You will have a happy
New Year.
Number five, relax.
Relax.
In verse number six, he says, "Relax.
Don't be anxious about anything.
Wow.
But in everything by prayer and petition
with thanksgiving, present your requests
to God.
And when you do that, what will happen?
The peace of God, which transcends all
human understanding, will guard your
heart and your minds in Christ Jesus."
As we are faced with the vicissitudes of
life, as Pastor White would say,
instead of being anxious and worried, we
should take it all to the Lord in
prayer,
thanksgiving, supplication, all manner
of prayers, and then leave it there.
After that, relax.
Jesus asked a very simple question in
Matthew chapter six, verse 27. "Who of
you by worrying can add a single hour to
your life?"
"Who of you by being anxious, by being
worried, can add a single hour to your
life?" The obvious answer is that
nobody.
Paul therefore advises, "Don't be
anxious
about anything, but in everything by
prayer and petition with thanksgiving,
present your requests to God. And then
the peace of God
will keep your heart."
I like the testimony of brother Charles.
Wow.
That was an opportunity to be anxious.
That was a chance
for our brother to be totally
devastated.
And he was. But in the midst of that,
he's telling this doctor, "Just go. The
machine is going to work."
That is trusting in God in situations
where you are not supposed to trust.
That's why it is called a peace that
surpasses
all understanding, because it is in a
situation where you are not supposed to
be peaceful. And yet you are peaceful
enough to think
and reason out that God can still deal
with this situation,
irrespective of what the doctors are
saying.
So, relax in the Lord. By relaxing here,
we don't mean that you will not feel a
sense of, you know, now what is going to
happen and so on, but that even in the
midst of your trouble, there's a
tranquil that comes into your heart
because you know God has a way.
God will come through somehow.
Let me not bore you with too many of my
own stories.
But relax.
Don't be anxious.
And you will
enjoy a happy
New Year.
The things that rob us of
joy, the things that rob us of
happiness,
are these kinds of things.
But when we have brought them to the
Lord in prayer,
it is possible to relax in the Lord and
know he's going to do it.
Refocus your thinking. Verse number
eight.
"Finally, brothers,
whatever
is true, whatever is noble, whatever is
right, whatever is pure, whatever is
lovely, whatever is admirable, if
anything is excellent or praiseworthy,
think about these things."
It is a fact that the thoughts you
entertain in your mind will influence
your perspective to life. Is that true?
If you consistently think negative
thoughts, your life is most definitely
going to be negative.
If you are a pessimist who only sees the
glass half full
or half
half empty. Half empty. That's the
pessimist.
Your life will always be half empty.
You know me, me, you know me. I'm just
like that. You know, everybody's moving
on. I don't know me, I'm stuck.
Who said you are stuck?
When your God is not stuck.
You are not stuck.
Your time is coming. Hallelujah. Your
time is coming.
Peninnah was getting children like rats.
Do you know the story of Peninnah?
And the Bible says, "And she got another
one."
And she the other And she got another
one.
And she got another one. And you know,
every time she got another one, she went
to Hannah
and said, "What is wrong with you?
I thought you women are supposed to do
what?
To get children.
What is wrong with you?"
And
you would imagine that God would now
stop her from getting another one
because of her attitude. She goes and
does what? And gets another one.
And so she just keeps getting children,
getting children. Hannah in the meantime
has no
child.
No child.
And so she's struggling with this
reality.
But you know,
Hannah had a different perspective to
life.
Hannah knew that there's a God in
heaven.
Children
are a blessing from the Lord.
They are a gift from his hand.
So, one time she's in church
in occasion like this one,
and she's there praying.
And Pastor Barasa says, "Everyone, let
let's stand and pray and let's move."
And Hannah is seated there.
And her mouth is moving. So, Pastor goes
to her say,
"Woman, if you have taken a little
too much, why did you come to church?"
And poor woman says, "Pastor,
it is not wine.
I am pouring my heart
to the Lord."
It is then that Pastor says, "May the
Lord answer your prayers."
And the Bible says, "A year later,
she had a son."
The son of Hannah is called Samuel.
The sons of Peninnah, we don't know
their names.
So, you may think you are stuck.
But when your son comes, will have a
name.
Hallelujah.
When your son comes, will have a name.
You are not stuck. When your job comes,
it will have a name.
When your husband comes, will have a
name.
When you say, "I'm Mrs. So-and-so,"
people say,
"You are the one."
When you know when they say, "I'm Mrs.
So-and-so," AND SAY, "OH."
PASTOR,
WHEN THE LORD comes through, he gets you
through.
So, don't worry. Don't worry.
So, Paul tells these people,
think positively.
Change your attitude. Look at life
differently. Life is not as bad as you
imagine. God is in control. God is on
the throne.
The Bible says, as a man thinketh, so is
he.
There are five ways
through which thoughts
enter your mind.
Five ways
which you are taught
when I was in class something.
One is through
seeing.
The other one is through
hearing. The other one is through
touching. The other one is through
smelling. I can see now you are with me.
The other one is through
tasting.
Those are how thoughts enter
your mind.
You see something, you think something.
You hear something,
you think something.
You touch something,
You smell something,
you think something.
You taste something,
That is how thoughts enter
into your mind.
But two are very significant.
Seeing
and hearing.
Those ones will affect your mind. So, be
careful what you see
and what you
hear.
Be careful what you see and what you
hear, because those are going directly
into your mind.
They are powerful.
David was a righteous man.
So righteous that God referred to him as
a man after my own heart. That is God
speaking, not people.
David was a righteous man.
A man after God's own heart.
One day David is stretching out
on the balcony
of his house.
Palace. He's a king.
And what happens? He sees something.
And what happens? He thinks something.
That's how a man after God's own heart
fell.
Because he saw
something. And what happened?
He thought something.
And the thought he thought
was not a good thought.
From there, every thought that was
coming was a bad one.
The first thought was, get that lady for
me.
The next thought is that
kill the husband. The next thought is
marry this one.
And he was going down and down and down.
Those of you who are caught up in
pornography,
you are seeing wrong things.
And when you see wrong things,
you begin to think
wrong things.
You cannot be seeing, because David was
a man after
God's own heart. His name was written
in the book of life.
But when he saw something,
he did what? He thought something. You
cannot see something
on the internet. You cannot see
something on your phone. You cannot see
something on pictures and magazines and
not
think something.
You cannot hear dirty music
and not think
something.
So, Paul writes to the
Philippians and says,
here is a test
to know
simple test to know what should occupy
your mind.
Ask yourself, is it true?
Is it noble?
Is it right?
Is it pure?
Is it lovely?
Is it admirable? Is it excellent? Is it
praiseworthy?
If the answer is yes to any of those
questions, Paul says, think about such
things.
If the answer is no,
stop thinking about such things. Even
now,
I know some of you are thinking.
Don't think those things.
Think the right things. Finally,
redirect your walk. I wish we had time
we could have expounded all of this, but
finally,
as we close,
the seventh and final advice is redirect
your walk. Paul tells the Philippians in
verse number nine,
whatever you have learned
or received or heard from me or seen in
me,
put into practice. I don't know whether
I can tell you that,
because some of you have seen bad things
in me.
But
he says,
the things you have seen, the things you
have heard, the things you have learned,
and as a church at Cittam, we have tried
to teach you good things. We have tried.
And we continue to try. Please put them
into practice. Even tonight, I am
teaching you some good things, I hope.
Don't just go there and say the cashier
was
good.
What was powerful. We were blessed.
Are you together?
Paul says, put these things into
practice.
Put these things into practice. Whatever
you have learned, whatever you have
received, whatever you have heard,
whatever you have seen, put them into
practice.
And he says, if you do that, what will
happen?
The end of that verse.
Oh, it's no longer on the screen.
What will happen? Verse number nine.
No.
Now you are saying what you are not
seeing.
Please see what is written.
The God of peace, not the peace of God.
The God of peace will be with you.
Did pastor talk about God being with
you?
Yes.
Pastor Obara talked about God's presence
going with us.
Paul concludes by saying that if you put
these things into practice, what will
happen?
The God of peace will be with you.
Paul tells the believers to be intimate
in their relationship with God, to be
practical in their walk with the Lord.
The implication is that our lives should
be lived according to what we have
learned, what we have received, what we
have heard, what we have seen.
It is only then that we can know the
truth, and the truth will set us free.
Two things I want to point out out of
that text of passage and we close.
I'm sure many of us would be wondering
whether this is practical. Practical. It
is practical.
That's why our theme for this year is
not by power,
not by might, but by the spirit of the
Lord.
Two things you will observe in verse
number seven and verse number nine.
Verse number seven says,
and the peace of God, which transcends
all understanding, will guard your
hearts and your minds in Christ Jesus.
Okay? If you are not anxious about
everything. Then verse number nine says,
and the God of peace will be with you.
What is the common word in those two
verses?
Peace.
How many of you want peace
in 2019?
Peace is what brings happiness.
When you are at peace, you can enjoy
life.
Pastor Mkoa,
when you are at peace, you can enjoy
life.
God promises
in his word
that if we leave out
anxieties and all these things that are
happening, the peace of God, which
surpasses all human understanding, will
guard our hearts and minds.
So, your heart is guarded, your mind is
guarded, you are okay. In other words,
there's a tranquility that will surround
your heart and your mind, such that no
matter what comes your way, you have an
inexplicable peace.
Peace.
You are at rest.
But that is what is called the peace of
God.
Will guard your heart and your mind in
Christ Jesus. But more than that,
it is not just the peace of God.
Is the God of peace.
Hallelujah.
The God of peace now will not just guard
your heart and mind, but will be with
you everywhere that you go.
I will be with you
everywhere that you go. Let me tell you
brothers and sisters,
I want to guarantee this one.
And
I put down my own life.
If any of you practices these seven
things,
and you come to the end of the year and
you're not happy, please come and see
me.
This is
satisfaction
guaranteed.
Hallelujah.
Do these seven things according to this
scripture,
and you are at peace from January
to December.
January to December.
Can we list them and then I finished?
Number one.
If you do those seven things
and still you are not happy,
then we need to take you to ICU. No.
Because God has guaranteed.
You are holding no one with grudges with
anybody.
You are relaxed in the Lord. Any people
fighting around you, you are helping to
reconcile them. You are not anxious
about anything. You are gentle with
every person you meet. Surely, what else
does anybody need to be happy in the new
year?
This Sunday we'll now talk about not by
power,
not by might,
but by the spirit of the Lord.
To see just how God has committed
himself
to help us in this journey.
So that
this thing can happen. And I want to
guarantee
that it is possible to live a happy life
in 20 19. Hallelujah.
Happy New Year.
Amen.
Come on. Come on.